Till now, what we have done is we have
done producer, we have done
the proper setup of cluster, we have
done consumer, consumer groups. And I
think we are in
uh you can say that one of one level
deeper, like uh we know the internals,
how Kafka works, right? So, we all are
on same page.
Now, the next part is the Kafka stream,
which is very, very important. So, till
now, whatever we have done, the current
flow is that producer publish an event.
Events is stored in
particular topic partition.
Consumer read the event from the
partition,
process them, like send notification.
So, this is generally what we have done.
So, now, before we uh start Kafka
stream,
understand its architecture, syntax, and
all, and the flow,
we need to first understand
what are the use cases where
Kafka stream
is useful.
Because that need to be clear. And
today, in this short video, I will cover
this part only.
So, let's uh start.
So, from above flow, we can easily
notice few things from this flow, what
we have already done.
In Kafka consumer,
each event is processed independently,
means no memory of previous event or
messages required. So, yes, if you have
10 events, you have a consumer,
uh let's say it read one event,
send notification. Second event, send
notification. Third event, do something,
send notification, likewise.
So, each event is independent.
Output depend on current event only, and
there is no need to remember anything
from the previous event or message.
So, this is known as a stateless
processing. What we have done till now.
But,
what if we need stateful processing?
So, in interview,
there are many scenarios which uh or not
even in interviews, you can say that in
real world when you're working,
there are many use cases where you need
to have a stateful processing. What does
it stateful processing say is
the output depend on the previous
events, too. So, it's your current event
plus your previous events, also.
So, we need to remember the states from
the previous messages, also. So, it's
not now independent on the current
event. So, you have to store
certain estate from the previous
messages, also. That's what it known as
a stateful processing.
Now, because of this stateful processing
or whatever we have done in Kafka
consumer, that will not work because
Kafka consumer is designed for stateless
processing.
Okay. So, what we have done is right,
one event comes, we do certain
processing. Then again, another event
comes, we do certain processing. Then,
it's a stateless. Means it
each event processing do not depend upon
the previous
event. Okay.
So, the real-world problems which
interviewer or you might face in
day-to-day work is
real-time aggregator. This is one use
case.
So, let's say interviewer say that
we need to find out in real time the
total revenue per customer. So, you have
multiple customers,
but you need to find out that and events
are coming that uh customer one
purchase, let's say for 50 rupees,
customer two purchase for 30 rupees,
customer one purchase for 70 rupees. So,
it's happening. Okay. So, our
requirement is in real time we need to
find out the total revenue per customer.
Like customer one, total sales, let's
say $100. Customer two, $150.
And another use case is real-time
leaderboard you have to do. So, that
also can be done through Kafka stream.
Generally, this is also can be solved
through Redis
jet set
sorted set.
But, with Kafka stream also it is
possible to do. Real-time leaderboard,
let's say user 350 points till now.
Let's say user A till now has solved two
problems only. So, 35 points. User B has
solved only one problem, let's say 15
points, likewise. Just an example.
So,
building this with
plain Kafka consumer, what we have done
till now is not easy. So, one approach
we might be doing to do to solve this
real-time aggregation is
storing the state in memory. So, now
let's say this is how we used to do,
right? The Kafka consumer. We have at
the rate Kafka listener, the topic.
And each one by one event we come and we
do process.
So, one thing we are doing is storing
the state in memory. So, we maintain a
map in memory
to store the state of the messages.
Okay. So, now let's say consumer one
till now total sale is $10. So, I have
put into this revenue map. Now, another
event comes, let's say consumer one
again, $20. So, what I will do is I am
updating this map itself. So, consumer
one, now it update to $30. So, this
information is stored in the in-memory
map. So, that is our one approach if you
are going with a plain Kafka consumer.
So, the problem is
what if application crash?
So, now let's say, for example, you have
already processed 1 lakh events
and you have built this map C1 C2 C100
they have like certain this one. Now,
what if your application crash itself?
So, your memory in memory gone?
Now,
you have when the
this is assigned
uh to some other node or when a new
server comes up,
they have to build this map again. So,
they have to replay
the event from offset zero, then only
you can get this map back again. So, you
have to replay from offset zero in case
of application crash because your in
memory
data will go.
Another is multiple instance. So, now
let's say for this order event has two
partition, partition zero, partition
one.
order-events
Now, in case you have two consumer,
consumer
one, consumer two. So, they let's say
both are taking one partition each.
So, now what would happen is consumer
one is maintaining in memory map.
Consumer two is also maintaining some in
memory map. So, it has data for let's
say
uh user one, user two. It has user
three, user four.
So, they both have partial data.
Okay? And they need the capability of
sharing the information to each other.
But, in case of multiple instances,
each instance
maintain partial data as each instance
read from different partition.
That is another problem.
So, you might be thinking that okay,
instead of in memory map, what if I go
with the approach two, that is storing
the state in MySQL?
Now, understand that now what we are
doing is from let's say MySQL
repository, we are
reading by ID.
We are adding whatever, let's say
uh we have to update its state. So,
earlier was $10, now we are doing plus
the current $20 and we are updating its
state.
So, this is get call.
This is, let's say,
not get call, this is your, let's say,
select query.
This is your
update query in MySQL. Now, the problem
is that in case of Kafka event,
for each Kafka event, we are doing
select and then we are doing update. So,
let's say we have 1 lakh events per
second.
We have per second, then we need
1 lakh select query, 1 lakh update query
per second.
So, now our database become the
bottleneck because this is a network
call.
So, there is again a problem.
So, this is just a one problem, the
real-time aggregation. That is just one
thing.
But, there are many other use cases,
let's say, window operation. What if
interview says now, let's say somehow
you solve this?
Okay.
Uh using, let's say, in memory
plus persistence, something you combine
and you resolve this. Now, let's say
what if interview says, "Hey, I need
window operations also." Means, let's
say, total revenue in last 5 minutes
only.
Now, what we have to do? Now, we need to
track the time stamp manually. We need
to expire the old entries manually.
Okay, only we have to consider the
latest 5 minutes.
Then, multiple instance, each is see
partial window data. So, let's say again
the same thing, part two partition if
you have and you have two consumers,
both reading from different partition.
So, it has partial data of the 5
minutes, let's say, only one, two. It
has partial data of the 5 minutes. Let's
say 3,4.
Okay? So, they have partial data and
they need
a distributed sharing something
mechanism.
Okay? So, window operation is also one
more challenge.
Another challenge which interviewer can
put is like you need a joining of two
tables. Let's say from order
you
take out a customer ID.
Now, from that customer ID, you need to
join the customer profile
uh
topic
and you need to fetch the customer name.
So, what we are saying that
we have to enrich
certain more with more information.
So, we are doing a joining between two
topics, order event and customer
profile.
So, if you go with the plain Kafka
consumer, again the same problem will
come as let's say if you have let's say
partition zero, for example, and only
one consumer one. It is reading this
partition.
One thing you need is that you need to
maintain whenever any consumer profile
data comes, it need to maintain a map.
Let's say, for example,
that okay, for this consumer ID
uh C1,
this is the data.
No name, something
object. Okay? Similarly, it has to
maintain everything.
And now, when the order event comes, it
has to look up this map.
But, the problem is same. What if the
app crash?
Then you have to read the customer
profile,
you have to replay from the offset zero.
So, always there is a problem.
Okay? So, one thing is you need to
maintain the map for the customer
profile.
Second is if there is an appli-
application crash, this map will go
away. Then you have to rebuild it
from replaying offset zero.
And another is multiple consumer
instance. That is also another same
problem.
Let's say
consumer A
maintain
partition zero of both the topic. Let's
say order events and consumer profile
both have two partitions.
P0 P1 P0 P1. Both topic has two
partition.
Now consumer A
taking care of partition zero of both
this topic. Okay? Similarly consumer B
taking care of partition one of both the
topic.
Now what happened is that
consumer is maintaining in memory map
for this consumer profile.
Let's say it is maintaining its consumer
three consumer four. It is maintaining
consumer one consumer two.
Okay? Now let's say in consumer A
order event
in the partition zero it comes and it
required consumer four
ID. Now it need
consumer four ID details. Will it get in
its local map?
No.
Okay? So it is consumer four data is
present into consumer
B.
So there is no way it can access its
local map. So we need a distributed
state sharing mechanism also. So we have
to build that also.
So if we go ahead and try to manually
solve all of this with normal Kafka what
we have done
we will end up doing or you can say that
building a state management. Windowing
joins the crash recovery.
And the scaling. All these things we
have to keep building it and ultimately
we will create a stream framework
itself.
So Kafka stream provide all of these
things itself.
Okay? So, we need to very clear that in
which scenarios
Kafka stream is helpful.
Okay? So, these are just some use cases.
Real-time aggregation, window operation,
join. So, these are some There could be
many more.
And yes, now I will And before in the
next topic, I will come up with the
architecture
of Kafka stream.
So, if you have not seen the previous
video, I would say that highly recommend
that actually
at least
go and check Kafka
consumer.
So, we have to be very clear with Kafka
consumer because Kafka stream also uses
the same, you can say that,
infrastructure itself.
So,
the prerequisite of this would be like
Kafka consumer understanding, in-depth
understanding how Kafka consumer works,
then understanding the Kafka stream
would be little easy. We would be able
to connect the dots.